[Music]
thank you hello and welcome to hollow
talk the internet radio broadcast for
lasers and holography enjoyed by
listeners throughout the world I'm Frank
defreitis and I'll be your host for each
installment bringing you news guests and
everything holographic now
enjoy the latest show
[Music]
hello Mary yes how are you it's Frank de
Freitas hi Frank good you got my email I
taken yeah I just got it a little while
ago I figured I'd go up and make a cup
of tea and come down and get things
hooked up to give you a call okay why
don't you tell the listeners right away
about your two shows since in case we
have anybody out there that listens to
the first five minutes and then cuts it
off
uh one one is a
May 5th only at the hollow center in
Long Island City New York and that's
called shelf life and in that one I'm
convicted
I've got about six six paintings and
about six Holograms and the Holograms
are all work I did in 1999-2000.
and then the second
in Brunswick Maryland that's actually
closer to you I think is that just
across from Harpers Ferry oh okay A
little corner there it's the last stop
on the mark train out of DC
that's a little show it's called the
Sundance
gallery and my sister runs it so we're
doing a little well you know I've got
about 20 paintings I'm showing there and
it's also so
yeah my father would have been 100 years
old this year and uh who was a painter
as well yeah so we've done some little
things made a few prints of some of his
paintings in my family's coming up
so it'll be just
be just fun I think I haven't sweated
too much about either of them so well
I'll have links to the Holo Center if
you have a link to the gallery
uh Maryland actually
um uh no but uh it can there's
information on my web yes uh
www.maryharman.com and I'll have a link
to your site as well
and if anyone goes to type that in it
it's
h-a-r-m-a-n if you type in
h-a-r-m-o-n you get a real estate agent
in Ohio oh is that right Mary Harmon
h-a-r-m-o-n I'll try that yeah she sells
real estate I did find a Harman Cemetery
in Ohio
greatness h-a-r-m-a-n we were born in
Ohio right I was born in Putin County
Ohio that's a rural areas that Amish
country no it's German they
basically
[Music]
people there at work are in southern
Ontario
what was he doing I'm sorry he he was
picking tobacco okay oh tobacco in Ohio
huh Belgium
Southern Ontario to work in the tobacco
fields
and um and then he went down to
Ohio
I worked in the I think was the beat the
Beats then
but the immigrants
and ended up staying married my mother
and stayed so it's a yeah very very
German community
so who didn't speak any at all when they
started school the same here in
Pennsylvania yeah yeah with the Amish
and Pennsylvania Dutch and German yeah
not too far from that where I am here in
Allentown
in fact one of the um uh during World
War II one of our local towns was
because of all German speaking raided by
another
oh really
it never ends
people will be talking about the same
thing hopefully not but you know
2180 or something
if we last
your paintings are absolutely beautiful
I know this is a holography show but I
have to comment to let people also visit
you know the web page that you have for
your painting
they're gorgeous
thank you yeah I I've uh I've really
been spending a lot of time I think the
last 10 years has really been painting
and again High realism and and uh and
that's I think I
illusion you know
illusions of Ria of the world we live in
right now so it's political and personal
I guess very becoming more and more
political these shows both
both and down here
become very political for me yeah
would I be correct in saying
that the uh the difference that I
noticed between the paintings and
and work that you've done with
hologography is that the holography
seems to have a
darker emotional tint to it
um
yes yeah I think so
um I think the paintings are very dark
as well I think everything the paintings
have gotten a lot darker since 2000. why
do you think that is
the world we live in okay yeah you know
I
um uh to well the the show with the show
in New York shelf life is really also a
look at you 62 years old and it was sort
of an inventory of where I am right now
and what I what I've done and what I
haven't done
uh and um that's the darkness
Darkness you know it's just here we are
we live in the same age of uh
accumulation and greed you know and
there's war going on yet so
so this was supposed to be the Aquarius
if I remember right well I'm not too far
behind UNH yeah yeah and I came up uh I
left this
57. I have to go the draft Dodger so I'm
an uh I'm an American expatriate I
filmed my U.S citizenship uh
new involvement in that ever since you
know it hasn't yeah
it has gotten worse so yeah well I think
in the 60s that's one of the things I've
been
bidding about a lot is is what we
thought we could accomplish you know we
thought we were going to change the
world right
here we are
um
so the paintings in in
the still lives have been
a lot getting a lot darker a lot of them
are about accumulations
and uh all my Optics I don't know if you
noticed in some of the ones I put up on
the website for the Maryland show
are sort of on the edge
The Edge there's a lot of fear in them
[Music]
you have a few repeating themes in some
of your paintings like string
you know which goes over to the
Holograms as well you know dice yeah
number of paintings that have Dyson what
did that what does that represent or is
that something that you prefer to just
let the viewer interpret no it I think
it started all I was when I was doing uh
the ones you saw in New York the
vanitoss paintings the Dutch still
a lot of symbols of mortality dice are
dice are is symbolic of Fate as is a
deck of cards say
um I use I found one one thing I really
like with the rubber band I have a lot
of things
uh whether it's vegetables
you'll see you'll see that a lot rubber
band strings is then sort of a same
thing
it
is just a loose rubber band laying on in
the foreground or the rubber band is
going to be wrapped around a bunch of
vegetables so it's it represents well
we're all we're all bound up and
so you'll see a lot of those little
symbols watches you know time again as
well yeah just just to remind us of our
mortality yeah when I would see one of
the paintings for
to me it was a counter with vegetables
tied up and here it has all this meaning
behind it that I didn't get when I
viewed it
and now people can hear the meaning
behind it it becomes more meaningful to
them when they see it
yeah yeah well I hope you know it's
it's nice when it comes through I think
they come through in different levels I
mean you can either look at something on
the surface and you know so it's a nice
looking pair but uh
uh
uh you also have this other deeper
meanings meetings behind it you know so
I think that's how I've always tried to
do my work even with holography you know
you can look at it in different ways
painting is very representative and
holography is very
real I mean the object that you do a
photography that's what it is
make the switch from one to the other
and sometimes even combine them well I I
think of painting is that's an illusion
um of two-dimensionality I'm I take a
real object and I make a two-dimensional
illusion of it and
I was making a three-dimensional
face face
it was an interesting show that I had in
the 80s with another artist here in the
Lehigh Valley of Pennsylvania
and they combined me with an artist that
took 3
of them in such a way that they became
flat and then they had my Holograms
there which was a flat surface that
showed three dimensions I thought that
was a nice pairing that's very that's
good yeah I like that idea I think
that's what that's what I've played with
a lot as well I like I like going
between mediums in that way you know
um yeah
yeah but someplace on your one of your
websites you said you said the thing
about you didn't you didn't just do
objects to represent objects yeah I try
not to yeah yeah
you know I I agree with you completely
there you know has to be something more
I mean and why why make a hologram
it has to be a reason what is
photography give to that object
and and to me it's it's been the number
one transparency I don't usually back
the hologram
I like it as bright as possible so
they're transparent yeah even if they're
floating behind the glass then I can put
other objects within that same volume so
so two objects can occupy the same
which is not possible to do in any
exactly exactly you know so that's what
that's where then you beat photography
so you're not you're not just
replicating in
without
something without moving on to
technology your glass must be
holographic plates must be extremely
clear I remember seeing one of yours
with a light bulb and a figurine that
sort of reconstructs in the light bulb
but it almost sounds like a a clear
piece of cover glass rather than a
hologram that's in front I wish I knew I
I have no idea how I did those it was a
series I did
um I think I was using Doris Villas lab
New York and and I didn't know much
about holography and I the only thing I
could figure out is possibly that I
really had my exposure times really low
or the developing times
which you know something that I didn't
get all that noise on the glass yeah and
I haven't been able to replicate it
since you know well I mean I haven't
really taken the time in all fairness to
play around with it that
is
but yeah I haven't gotten that I mean I
tried uh I tried oh taking some
transfers and then uh bleaching them out
and things like this you know that whole
but that doesn't do any
yeah so yeah I wish I could I'll figure
that out again someday hopefully but
that work with Doris veal was at the
Hope Street series that's right yeah
they're interesting
yeah yeah then I had those floating so
then you could put a photograph behind
it and then the image would look like
it's floating through oh I got photos of
Windows and things and it would float
right through the image I liked your
memento
is that object or is that a photograph
uh because the objects that you've used
if it is a photograph it looks very
three-dimensional I think there's a key
hanging yeah there's a few other pieces
of the combination of both yeah
it's very you know very uh the depth
maybe it's only about an inch on that
one just a very shallow depth behind the
behind the hologram
the Hologram was in the Wendy's little
boxes yeah and then I put um photographs
and uh oh just bits and pieces yeah it
was very successful in that the images
do create feelings Within I'm not sure
of the feelings that I have would be the
same feelings of someone else but you
know especially the momento I felt quite
a bit of tension and almost uh
oh really you know and thank you in that
piece there well that was a that was a
little strange one I had also a photo in
there of uh of my mother's my mother my
when my mother died
uh sort of the week before she died she
let us know that our grandfather wasn't
really our grandfather and she had been
illegitimate and it was this little
secret she was hiding and she came out
with this photo of uh of what she
father
the German soldier from World War one
and so there's so there's an image like
you know I put that in there of this
little German soldier in the background
yeah so you know there was a lot of
feeling in that one I guess and it's all
parts of my mother the key from the
house in Ohio the Old Farmhouse oh okay
I think objects have
uh objects have little lives of their
own sometimes I think everything has a
life of its own even a rock yeah
you know and we're all connected to it
yep that's holography in a nutshell
really even thought
people think that thought is something
separate from the universe that
surrounds us but thought is an integral
part of the universe and it falls under
the same laws of the universe
which means you can attract to you
whatever it is that you're thinking
about and that happens to a lot of
people this is this is another idea that
I that when I started doing this show
for New York the shelf life series it's
involved right now I'm working a lot
with digital transparencies
and uh
putting objects within the digital
transparencies in the same way that I
would use the hologram
but the idea that occurred you know this
whole business with Iraq I was really in
thinking of my own what what's my own
responsibility for this you know and uh
yeah we all are because we're all part
of the world you know we're all
consumers
yeah we all bought into the stock market
and
um in the same way that you know you're
saying we're all all the objects in the
world you know when someone dies there
we're affected
we're all part of the same uh atomic
structure yeah it's like a sphere yeah
yeah where are you living if we you know
if we live in a global Society we're
gonna have to accept some responsibility
for all these things that are happening
too yeah yeah
anyway sometimes I have I have hopeful
thoughts about that and other times it's
like
maybe it's just
they don't know
I don't know
I don't know I don't know if this is
I've always been fairly optimistic but I
just had a grandchild this
congratulations yeah and that's you know
you really start thinking you know what
are we doing and uh maybe this is
something different you know anyway wow
yeah I got your email about that I was
going to see if you were okay later
tonight and then just you know if you
wanted to do it tomorrow but today's
great you sound good you sound in good
spirits
oh yeah I'm nearly finished with all
this shipping and sending uh work to the
show so I can I'm gonna go off to my
cabin for a couple of days and sit in
the sun that's nice you
know
yet we just had ice and snow and
you know it's still Winter's hanging on
you know no no we had the ice in snow
last week today's the first day of sun
okay well maybe uh we'll have the same
luck here when was the last time you
were working with philography has it
been a few years for you yeah
uh well I did I think I you know after
the work you saw in 2000 I went to the
hall Center I think it was 2003. I had
this I had a series of
uh more objects I was doing and I had
built these ceramic uh uh call them
retired generals they were just um
jesters
parody on boys
and uh this stuff just weren't that
great my masters weren't that great so
my transfers weren't that great and
I didn't really do any more with those
and
I noticed you're doing some work with um
with uh digital yeah
yeah a little LCD panels yeah yeah and
they're very inexpensive now you know
you know they're very inexpensive that
interests me and they hook right onto
the back of your computer they work like
your monitor does in fact you can plug
your monitor into them so that you can
see what it is you're working on while
the LCD panels on
them yeah should look into it or you
know send me an email I'll send you some
information about it well I noticed you
use
um you do a lot with Photoshop photo
transparencies that's what I've been
doing and then I started doing some
photo
uh material called image on and using
the sun to to develop oh okay the plates
onto this
material and then do
and I actually got a print a photo
prints in the New York show in that but
um the LCD that sounds interesting
because do you ever make digital uh
positive transparency have you tried
that rather than just film
digital positive transparencies rather
than the film no I have not done that I
have not done that the um and it's it
seems I don't know it's been working for
me to do the photo uh transfers but yeah
I don't know if it would work
I would probably have to Outsource
of those files to get you know good
gradation of
and things like that rather than relying
everything you can do right you know
it's the output device I just have a
and I don't think the printer is capable
of of giving me the tonal gradations
that you know I would have on the screen
yeah you're probably right yeah those
stuff I've been just using
a printer
then I
did I think it would be fine for line
art you know Lionheart would be fine
well I I no I I should show you uh
show you uh one of the prints I did do
from one of the paintings and I did it
in black and white so that goes on to a
mylar
inkjet like it goes on to my Lord yeah I
just used uh I just used uh overhead
transparency paper stay s you just start
playing around with it you know uh you
can just you can download so many
different curves you just have to keep
it really light I think you know like 20
what your normal uh you know do a
reversal in Photoshop and then yeah
and then maybe lighten it up by about 20
percent
yeah you can screen it I think you have
you have to and that's where you know
the dots you know yeah you have to be
careful if you're doing multiple
exposures that you don't get more a
patterns you know you use dots or
multiple exposures
yeah I'm curious about this
Health yeah
work you're doing yeah well anytime you
want to talk about it you know as a side
note be happy to uh maybe I have to sit
down with a cup of tea and give a call
or something oh that'd be great yeah
anything that you would say to any art
students out there
you know that might be thinking you know
let me give this a try
what would you say to them
do it you know I mean
which holography or painting or oh
holography yeah
yeah because I would think that a lot of
art students would go into thinking that
they're going to wind up on the cover of
art today or even something like
Newsweek or something but that's not the
reality well from what I hear that's the
problem
with professions I mean
I mean what the kids think well that's a
generalization and so yeah
that
is
a cheaper list so I can manage I'm not
making a lot from my page either yeah so
I'm trying some prints now
yeah holography I don't know you know
more you know you
you can do it you can do it cheaper than
I could
but uh
why why do you think that is
uh
if I wanted to get back into holography
I would probably do it that way I'd give
myself a little diode laser in the sand
table Yeah do it that way
um
discouraging you know
you know trying to get funding whatever
yeah exactly I don't get grants I've
never had a grant
no if I ever had if I ever needed money
for a box of 30 by 40 centimeter plates
or something I'd Foster work to do and
go out and do
I've never had a grant
[Music]
well and you know so you've probably
done a lot more work than a lot than
than a lot of people I know who who
won't do something because I
said yeah now yeah I don't know what the
I mean everyone has their own mindset
towards things but
I don't rely on very many external
things other than you know myself
sometimes
you know to that's the way to live yes
it's independent you know I guess
well we're coming up on 27 minutes is
there anything that you wish we had
talked about that we didn't
you know considering the audience of
course you know we've got school kids
that listen to this in their computer
labs at school
you've got scientists that are listening
to
you know physicists and Optical
engineers
hobbyists you have
you know I I don't think it makes
I think anybody that has just a passion
for what they do
and you know it doesn't matter whether
whether you're an artist or a scientist
or I mean a school kid can make
an artist can
you know yeah if you're just if you're
creative and you know you're looking for
something
to say to say basically either about
yourself or about the world we live in
you know and I think we're living in a
time when
when a lot more people should be talking
about hey there's something going wrong
with the world we're living in and don't
be afraid to just just stop yeah in
whatever way you can yeah exactly
exactly be a simple
and images that really move
you know I mean I use I I got some
images from from the internet that I
used in a lot of my photo transparencies
it was this little image of the
helicopters
a little Black Hawk helicopters that
jars and floating through
through tiles
and you know it was just it's something
that just speaks to me of a symbolic of
this
industrial world right now yeah
yeah so I use that and I use the glass
jar you know the ball jar
the bowl jar right yeah yeah I love that
too I don't know what it is about it the
Symmetry the the agility it's just
it's just become a container you know
well that's that's what I think artists
are art is you know we're all containers
for bigger things
I wonder if you would be I wonder if you
would be surprised at how many people
that are listening to this have no idea
what we're talking about when we say a
ball jar really oh sure
is that typically in Ohio and I think oh
no I don't think so I think it's more
generational I think chronologically
chronologically yeah
yeah yeah we have all the farmers
markets here to get fresh produce and
I was looking for some images of I've
got
charism
I got from my mother from the 30s they
were used to canned apple butter and
they had a great pattern in it I made a
couple Holograms of pattern in the jars
they're collector's items now oh it's
collecting ball jars Google it and
you'll see all the different kind of
glasses
yeah
I have Bicentennial ball jars it's got
1776 to 1976 on the ball jar
if you ever have use for something like
that let me know I'll put it in a box
and send it to me
well the the one the one jar that I've
been using I I think it's a yeah it's so
Ball mason jar and under underneath it
it says it says perfect Mason
in those in those letters that stand out
the jar you know and they catch the
Light so I've painted a couple of them
perfect Mason
I love your replica work
what is it a door or barn door or
something
is it a barn door or something or
whatever it was the door I found in um
somebody throwing it out what a piece of
work that is isn't that nice yeah that
that intrigues me more than anything I
believe for some reason it's just uh
that's that's I I think that particular
piece was really the basis for a lot of
my that was the basis for painting
originally I thought well what's the
difference if I just copied
copy you know and uh and then I realized
you know I so I painstakingly
replicated this six foot door five foot
you know I've still got this piece and I
did it sort of square by square I would
you know match completely match in in
color and everything and then when I put
these things standing side by side you
know there was something that happened
there's something in illusion you know
there's something in the crack between
the reality and illusion or the real
object and they lose an area object yeah
that says something
I'm not sure what
but it's
it's whether it's that next Dimension or
whatever you know well in this in this
day of biotechnology and cloning it's an
interesting piece
you know I have to come back to um
uh I come back I come through your wake
actually quite a bit because you do well
I visit my sister out in Washington oh
you should give me a call I will I would
Georgetown Hospital okay
I like that area yeah yeah we've I go
through Antietam and all those
places around there the battlefield
yeah anyway
so I'll stop by sometime anyway but
we'll be in touch okay all right take
care have a good weekend bye